# NAHEED ANJUM ARAFAT

naheed anjum@u.nus.edu | Mobile: +65-90196390 | 85 Circuit Road, #03-1019, Singapore 370085

## **RESEARCH INTERESTS**

I have prior experience and sufficient interest in the following domains. However I am flexible enough to work on a different domain of relevance.

- Topological data analysis: Exact and approximate computation of topological features of data, as well as their application in different domains.
- Graphs and Hypergraphs: Algorithmic aspects of graphs and hypergraphs and application of such structures on different domains.
- Optimization problems: Multi- and many-objective optimization problems.

#### **EDUCATION**

## **National University of Singapore (NUS)**

Singapore

PhD in Computer Science

Aug 2015 - Present (Thesis defended)

• Thesis: Analysis and generation of data with topology from combinatorial representations

## Bangladesh University of Engineering and Technology (BUET)

Dhaka, Bangladesh

Bachelors in Computer Science & Engineering; GPA: 3.79/4

May 2014

• Thesis: A Fuzzy Dominance Based Evolutionary Algorithm for solving many-objective optimization problems.

## **EMPLOYMENT HISTORY**

## **National University of Singapore**

Singapore

Research Fellow, Department of Information Systems & Analytics

July 2020 - Present

• Graph-theoretic modelling and analysis of co-evolving software ecosystems.

## **National University of Singapore**

Singapore

Research Assistant, Department of Computer Science

Nov 2019 - June 2020

• Random generation of hypergraphs with prescribed constraints.

## **United International University**

Dhaka, Bangladesh

Lecturer, Department of Computer Science

Jun 2014 - Jul 2015

• Prepared lecture notes and assignments. Conducted lectures and lab-sessions. Evaluated assignment submissions and exam-scripts. Devised and evaluated lab projects. Performed miscellaneous administrative duties.

#### **Software Global Consultancy**

Dhaka, Bangladesh

Part-time Developer

Jan 2014 - Mar 2014

• Developed cross-platform, educational mobile apps to teach kids handwriting.

#### RESEARCH EXPERIENCE

## Research Fellow

Department of Information Systems & Analytics, NUS

Assistant Professor UM Sungyong

July 2020 - Present

Department of Computer Science, NUS

Research Assistant Professor Tan Kian Lee Department of Computer Science, NUS Nov 2019 - June 2020

PhD Student

1101 2019 - Julie 2020

Supervisor: Associate Professor Stéphane Bressan

Jan 2016 - Present

Undergraduate research

Department of CSE, BUET

Supervisor: Professor Md Monirul Islam

Jan 2013 - May 2014

## TEACHING/MENTORING EXPERIENCE

## **Graduate Assistant**

NUS Jan 2016 - Present

#### • Tutored Courses-

- o Big Data Techniques and Technologies (BT4221): Dept. Of Information Systems and Analytics Aug 2019 sem.
- o Data Management and Warehousing (BT5110): Master Of Science Business Analytics Programme Aug 2019 sem.
- o Data Management and Warehousing (BT5110): Master Of Science Business Analytics Programme Aug 2018 sem.
- o Information Visualisation (CS5346): Dept. of Computer Science, School of Computing Jan 2018 sem.
- o Data Management and Warehousing (BT5110): Master Of Science Business Analytics Programme Aug 2017 sem.
- Programming Methodology (CS1010E): Dept. of Computer Science, School of Computing Jan 2017 sem.
- o Discrete Structures (CS1231): Dept. of Computer Science, School of Computing Aug 2016 sem.
- o Programming Methodology (CS1010E): Dept. of Computer Science, School of Computing Jan 2016 sem.

#### Lecturer

United International University

Jun 2014 - Jul 2015

#### • Instructed Courses-

- o Advanced Programming Languages: Dept. of Computer Science Summer'14, Fall'14, Spring'15, Summer'15 trimesters.
- o Data Structures: Dept. of Computer Science Fall'14, Summer'15 trimesters.
- Discrete Mathematics: Dept. of Computer Science Summer'14 trimester.
- o Structured Programming Language: Dept. of Computer Science Spring'15 trimester.
- Electric Circuits: Dept. of Computer Science Fall'14, Spring'15, Summer'15 trimesters.

#### Mentor

PhD student Jan 2019 - Mar 2019

• Debabrata Mahapatra: Held consultation and discussion sessions about the theories and applications of Topological Data Analysis.

#### RESEARCH PUBLICATIONS

#### • Conference Proceedings

- Naheed Anjum Arafat, Debabrota Basu, Laurent Decreusefond, and Stéphane Bressan. Construction and random generation of hypergraphs with prescribed degree and dimension sequences. In *Database and Expert Systems Applications*, pages 130–145, Cham, 2020. Springer International Publishing
- 2. Naheed Anjum Arafat, Debabrota Basu, and Stéphane Bressan.  $\epsilon$ -net induced lazy witness complexes on graphs. 2019
- 3. **Naheed Anjum Arafat**, Debabrota Basu, and Stéphane Bressan. Topological data analysis with *ϵ*-net induced lazy witness complex. In *Database and Expert Systems Applications*, pages 376–392, Cham, 2019. Springer International Publishing
- 4. **Naheed Anjum Arafat** and Stéphane Bressan. Hypergraph drawing by force-directed placement. In *International Conference on Database and Expert Systems Applications*, pages 387–394, Cham, 2017. Springer International Publishing

## Journals

1. Siddhartha Shankar Das, Md Monirul Islam, and **Naheed Anjum Arafat**. Evolutionary algorithm using adaptive fuzzy dominance and reference point for many-objective optimization. *Swarm and evolutionary computation*, 44:1092–1107, 2019

## • Preprints

1. Naheed Anjum Arafat, Debabrota Basu, Laurent Decreusefond, and Stéphane Bressan. Construction and random generation of hypergraphs with prescribed degree and dimension sequences (extended version). arXiv preprint arXiv:2004.05429, 2020

#### **TALKS**

- BT4221 Guest lecture (NUS): Conducted two guest lectures on 'Practical data analysis using Amazon EMR and Sagemaker services' in August 2020 semester.
- BT5110 Guest lecture (NUS): Conducted a hands-on lecture on 'developing retail-sales data mart using Pentaho' in August 2018 semester, MSBA programme.
- E2S2-CREATE Seminar: Gave a talk on 'Topological Data Analysis' at E2S2-CREATE Seminar, Feb 2018 attended by 20+ researchers from E2S2 project funded by NRF.
- CS5346 Guest lecture (NUS): Conducted a lecture on 'Force-directed hypergraph drawing for data visualisation' in January 2018 semester at Dept. of Computer Science, School of Computing, NUS.

## **SELECTED SERVICES**

• Session Chair: Chaired two sessions at NUS SoC-Telecom ParisTech joint workshop on Data Sciences and Artificial Intelligence, April 2018 attended by 20+ researchers from Telecom ParisTech and NUS.

- Session Chair: Chaired two sessions at NUS School of Computing Research Workshop, March 2018 attended by professors and researchers from various countries in Asia.
- Co-organizer: Co-organized 8th International Conference on Software, Knowledge, Information Management and Applications (SKIMA), 2014 held at United International University, Bangladesh.

• Reviewer: SKIMA 2014

## **AWARDS & ACHIEVEMENTS**

- NUS Research Scholarship
- Teaching Assistant Training Certificate issued by the Centre for Development of Teaching & Learning (CDTL), NUS for completing training on applying 'Collaborative Learning' approaches.
- **Distinguished Poster Award** at Undergraduate Research Poster Presentation Workshop, Department of Computer Science and Engineering, BUET for presenting a poster titled 'Many-Objective Evolutionary Approach using Fuzzy Dominance with Bidirectional Bias'.
- Champion award for showcasing the project titled 'Cell phone operated mini-car with surveillance' at Inter-University Project Show (Hardware panel), CSE Festival, BUET.
- Talent pool Board scholarship for excellence in Secondary and Higher Secondary exams, Jessore Board, Bangladesh.

## **SKILLS**

- Languages: Python, Java, C, C++, Matlab, R, Processing, PHP
- Big Data Frameworks: Hadoop, Spark
- Data warehousing & Viz. Tools: Pentaho Data Integration, Tableau
- Databases: MySQL, PostgreSQL, Oracle
- Web Dev: HTML/HTML5, CSS/CSS3, JavaScript, JQuery, JQuery Mobile
- Excellent presentation skill and proficiency in technical writing (Latex).
- Ability to work independently as well as in a team.
- Ability to communicate effectively and methodically to produce deliverables.